<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Network on rapatao.com</title><link>https://www.rapatao.com/tags/network/</link><description>Recent content in Network on rapatao.com</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2022 12:00:00 -0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.rapatao.com/tags/network/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What is a Reverse Proxy?</title><link>https://www.rapatao.com/posts/2022-10/what-is-a-reverse-proxy/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2022 12:00:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://www.rapatao.com/posts/2022-10/what-is-a-reverse-proxy/</guid><description>A reverse proxy is a server that has as its main functionality to receive requests from an external network, usually the Internet, and forward them to servers on an internal network.
This server acts as the user&amp;rsquo;s entry point to your application, which allows you to perform various types of customization on the received request, such as changing the request parameters or rewriting the path (path) in a REST request.</description></item><item><title>What is a CDN (Content Delivery Network)?</title><link>https://www.rapatao.com/posts/2022-04/what-is-a-cdn-cdn-content-delivery-network/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 19:00:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://www.rapatao.com/posts/2022-04/what-is-a-cdn-cdn-content-delivery-network/</guid><description>A Content Delivery Network, can be described as a set of servers, distributed globally, with the purpose of providing content to users in an optimized way and in the shortest possible time.
The CDN servers are distributed in several locations, some of these servers tend to be located closer to the destination user than the origin server, which makes the distance that the data travel (physically) is smaller, consequently, delivered more fast.</description></item><item><title>Load Balancing: What is a load balancer?</title><link>https://www.rapatao.com/posts/2022-02/load-balancing-what-is-a-load-balancer/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 20:00:00 -0300</pubDate><guid>https://www.rapatao.com/posts/2022-02/load-balancing-what-is-a-load-balancer/</guid><description>Widely used in applications with high volume of simultaneous access, a load balancer is a computational resource used to perform load distribution between two or more servers of an application.
They are usually implemented using machines dedicated to this work, which can be physical or virtual, or by “software”.
Benefits Regardless of the model to be implemented, they aim to distribute the processing of an application among the available instances, seeking to optimize the use of computational resources, such as network, processing (CPU), memory usage, among others.</description></item></channel></rss>